Hey, בוקר טוב *boker tov*, we begin a new פרק perek? *perek*
today and we're on track.
So, we pick up on ט"ו עמוד amud... א' *tet-vav amud aleph*,
סדר תעניות ta'aniot *Seder Ta'aniyot*. So, whereas the last פרק perek. *perek*
the focus was on the fasting itself and on the order of
fasts, the three, the three, the seven for the תענית taanis ציבור
tzibbur. *Taanit Tzibbur*, this פרק *perek* has a lot to do with
the liturgy and with, I keep saying liturgy, with the תפילות tefillos.
*tefillot*,
and with how exactly what they would do special, you know things
that we've already seen that wasn't necessarily the fasting in itself, it
was the fasting as that's been translated into the whole sort of
communal experience. What was the פסוק *pasuk*? קראו צום קדשו עצרה *Kar'u
tzom kidshu atzara*, or was it, I get that reversed, I think
I got that right. Anyway, you know, that you call the fast
and then you make it a day of gathering and a day
of תפילות tefillot. *tefillot* and also a day of communal self-assessment
as we've seen. So that really is the focus of this פרק
*perek* and we start with what the people who put together the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, I don't mean the חז"ל Chazal, *Chazal*, I mean
the printers decided for some bizarre reason to put all of the
משניות *mishnayot* of this פרק *perek* together in the first משנה mishna
*mishna*. So we will read through this first משנה mishna's *mishna*, but
this really is all, it's almost the whole דף *daf* today is
the משנה Mishna *mishna* because it really is like the six or
seven משניות *mishnayot* stitched together. It's all of the משניות *mishnayot* of
the פרק *perek*. So let's begin. סדר תעניות ta'aniyot, כיצד *Seder Ta'aniyot
keitzad*? The order of the fasts, how is it? And again, interestingly,
in a way, you could say didn't we just do that, the
order, the three, the three, the seven? But this really means like
we would say like the פסח סדר *Pesach Seder*, like how do,
what is the agenda of the evening, you know, what is the
way things are organized for the fast? So that is, right, קדש
*Kadesh* or, so anyway, so this is the סדר *Seder*, what's the
סדר *Seder* for the תעניות ta'aniyot, *ta'aniyot*? How, what is the sort
of way in which you do the order of the day for
the fast days? So מוציאין את התיבה *motzi'in et hateiva*, you bring
out the ark. We referred to this yesterday, right, the תיבה teiva,
*teiva*. We know that the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is going, is assuming
and we'll see that when we get to the גמרא gemara *Gemara*,
that this is only in the last seven, but the משניות *mishnayot*
do not specify. It's going to describe the whole sort of, like
I said, order of the day, a lot of the תפילות tfilot
*tefillot* but things also not exactly תפילות *tefillot*, but the order of
the day. It's not going to identify for which fasts it's talking
about. Is it from the first three, the middle three, the last
seven? The גמרא gemara, *Gemara* will assume, will have a ברייתא *beraita*
that will say this is the last seven. Okay, but, but here
is the order. So you go ahead and you take out the
ark לרחובה של עיר *rechovah shel ir*, to the street of the
city. The רחוב *rechov* of the city really was like the public
square. It wasn't like some side street or something. This is like
the public square where you have your public gatherings. So they would
take it out to the public square. נותנים אפר מקלה על גבי
התיבה *notnim eifer mikleh al gabei hateiva*, and they would put ashes
that have of something burnt on top of the ark. Now you
might say why do you have to have the word אפר מקלה
*eifer mikleh*, ashes of something burnt? How else do you create ashes?
So if you take a look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* makes an important point. רש"י *Rashi* says the following.
אפר מקלה *eifer mikleh*, רש"י *Rashi* says אפר ממש ולא עפר *eifer
mamash velo afar*, we mean ashes, we don't mean dust. Why? Because
אפר סתם *eifer stam*, if it had the word אפר *eifer* without
the modifier, הוא עפר *hu afar*, that means dust, or could just
as easily mean dust. וכשם שאפר קרוי עפר *u'keshem she'eifer karui afar*,
as it says מעפר שריפת החטאת *me'afar sereifat hachatat*, right, good point.
It says from the dust of the burning of the sin offering,
but that's not dust, that's ashes. כך עפר קרוי אפר *kach afar
karui eifer*, so dust could be called ashes. סתם *Stam*. So therefore
והיינו דקתני אפר מקלה *ve'hainu d'katni eifer mikleh* is אפר שריפה *eifer
sereifa*. אי הוי תני אפר סתם הוי משמע עפר *Ei havei tani
eifer stam havei mashma afar*. So רש"י
*Rashi* makes a good point, you know, by אברהם *Avraham*, ואנכי עפר
ואפר *v'anochi afar va'eifer*, right? So two different things but it also
means like, you know, what does that mean? Like, we understand a
man is created, a person's created from dust, but what does it
mean he's saying when I'm ashes? You know, I mean I guess
if people would be cremated you could say and then so I'll
be ashes, but anyway. But it does show that those words are
used in like, sort of in conjunction. So it's quite interesting little
side point that if you want to be clear that you mean
ashes and not dust, you say אפר מקלה *eifer mikleh*. Okay, so
you put ashes על גבי התיבה *al gabei hateiva* on the top
of the ארון Aron, *aron*. ובראש הנשיא ובראש אב בית דין Av
Beit Din *u'verosh hanasi u'verosh av beit din* and you put it
on the top of the נשיא Nasi *nasi* and the top of
the אב בית דין Av Beit Din *av beit din*. Now the
נשיא Nasi *nasi* is, you know, the, like again, if this is
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, it would be that would be like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda הנשיא *Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi*, okay, and the person who's
the political head, and the אב בית דין Av Beit Din *av
beit din* is presumably the, you know, the rabbinic head. Right when
we have all of the זוגות *zugot* that preceded הלל *Hillel* and
שמאי *Shammai*, the two leaders, one was the נשיא Nasi *nasi* and
the other was the אב בית דין Av Beit Din. *av beit
din*. So of course what's a little bit strange is one minute.
So this is happening in one place or this is happening like
in every city, right? I mean, and or was this happening דוקא
where the in the town where there's the in the city where
there's the political seat of authority, where there's the rabbinic seat of
authority? So what would you do in a small city, in a
small town? So maybe it means it's really not clear and it's
not explicated. But I have to assume that it really means whoever
would be the appropriate people in that position for that town or
for that city. But meaning the sort of the political and religious
head of the city. So נשיא Nasi and אב בית דין Av
Beit Din sort of refer to the type of role that I
can come up with. But this is really, this is something that
would happen everywhere, wouldn't happen just in one centralized place.
Well why couldn't it have happened everywhere
and where the נשיא Nasi and the אב בית דין Av Beit
Din, are sitting?
Could be, could be.
But I know that we're doing this and then in the city
צפורי? Tzippori? Could be, could be.
Look, I also think that I'll say a word about why we're
going to, well let me do the next line and then why
we do it on the ארון, Aron. on these people, and then
the next line is: וכל אחד ואחד נותן בראשו. v'chol echad v'echad
noten b'rosho. And every individual also puts ashes on his head. Now,
so what are the ashes about? So presumably, I mean some people
have the מנהג minhag that a חתן chassan puts some ashes on
his forehead when he
at the wedding, part of the idea of נעלה ירושלים על ראש
שמחתנו, na'aleh Yerushalayim al rosh simchatenu, now you could say it refers
to the idea that the מקדש Mikdash was burned, but there also
seems to be the idea that ashes as some type of a
symbol of mourning.
So if that's true, not necessarily about being burned per se, although
רש"י emphasizes ashes not dust, but nevertheless, whatever it is, if it's
a symbol of mourning, right,
then everybody's in mourning. Okay, so we get that the people are
in mourning, certainly when it's going to or at least when it's
going to get to being really drastic, right, everybody adopts real practices
of mourning and it's like כבני אדם הנזופים למקום. k'vnei adam hanizufim
laMakom. At this stage, we're still in the תעניות ta'aniyot stage, so
it's not yet at that, but it's sort of that's sort of
on the horizon and there's that sense of it, of elements of
that might already be present. And presumably what they're mourning and they're
feeling tragic, right, you could just say all of this is to
make you feel like it's bad, it's really bad, right? So you
see this like burnt and things destroyed and it just evokes a
sense of like things are bad and it's a tragedy and we
have to really focus and pray and do תשובה. teshuvah. But I
also think that if you see it more again in this sort
of mourning state, it's about acknowledging specifically that what are we mourning,
we're mourning in a way the loss of the relationship or the
weakening of the relationship which in the end as we know if
if all of this happens and it doesn't help we're really going
to go into mourning over that, כבני אדם הנזופים למקום. k'vnei adam
hanizufim laMakom. So I think that's all part of what's going on
here. I think it's interesting in that respect that the ashes are
also on the ארון. Aron? Why are the ashes on the ארון?
Aron. So again, if you just wanted to sort of speak about
this in terms of like the psychological emotional impact, everybody's gathered, you're
going to pray, so it's sort of like holding them up in
the front of the ציבור. tzibbur Like just a way of presenting
this symbol to everybody, like facing the ארון. Aron, But I do
think, again, maybe I'm a little
bit being a little sort of midrashic here, but I do think
that it might be also symbolizing that God is in mourning as
well, the idea עמו אנכי בצרה, imo anochi b'tzara, very powerful idea
of חז"ל, Chazal right, that when there's a when when it's necessary
that we when we're suffering God is suffering. And if the relationship
for whatever reason is weakening and there's a distance that's created,
not we're feeling it and God is feeling it as well. And
so we're all in mourning over this situation. I think that that
could be a little bit of the symbolism. I think the idea
of the נשיא Nasi and the אב בית דין Av Beit Din,
also is like because this is not an individual issue, it's a
communal issue, and it's the leaders of the community that have to
really step up and take responsibility, right, so what have we done,
as we said before and we're going to that there's a whole
process about מעיינין במילי דמתא, me'aynin b'milei d'mata, that we assess what's
going on in the, what what we've done wrong as a community,
are there things we need to fix, are there wrongs that have
to be
righted? So, who's responsible in the end if things are going wrong?
It's the leadership of the community and I think that's specifically here
the נשיא Nasi and the אב בית דין. Okay, so the ashes
on these three: the ארון, aron the נשיא and the אב בית
דין and the people. And as and again just just be about
feeling bad but could also be the sense about
taking responsibility and a sense of mourning and who's in mourning and
so on. So that's step number one. Also by the way I
should say that taking the תיבה, teiva let's say something just for
one second about that, into the square. Why do you take it
into the square? Why don't you just do it in the שול?
shul? Is it the שול shul isn't big enough to hold everyone?
So maybe that's it, maybe you need to do it in the
square and you because it's a you need everyone everyone there. Maybe
also... And again, things that are done outdoors make more of a,
like the גמרא gemara said before, פרהסיא, parhesia, make more of a
big deal about it. But there could also be a little bit
of an idea that even God is in exile, like even the
תיבה isn't in its right place. So we're all feeling the sort
of the sense of distance and exile that's being
created at this moment. So that's step number one.
Yes, I was just looking at what was the text I had
pointed out previously about this. That is, the תורה Torah is not
supposed to be secluded in the בית כנסת, Beit Knesset, בית מדרש,
Beit Midrash, that the idea is to bring the תורה Torah out
to the square and both literally...
Oh,
that's interesting. So part of, like, do you mean connected to the
נשיא and the אב בית דין, maybe part of the problem is
that we have not brought the תורה Torah into our larger life
as much as we need to. Nice idea. Okay, so that's step
number one. Ashes, you're out in the street, everybody is sort of
feeling the weight and hopefully the responsibility of the situation. הזקן שבהם,
Hazaken shebahem, the elder among them, interestingly that the elder's not necessarily
the נשיא or the
אב בית דין, but some one religious leader among them or maybe
just somebody who's good at as a דרשן, darshan, but the elder
among them אומר לפניהם דברי כיבושין, omer lifnechem divrei kivushin,
says in front of them words of כיבושין. kivushin. רש״י Rashi says
it words come from the word like to press olives, but it
means like words that are going to humble and stir people up
to be reflective is normally the connotations of the word דברי כיבושין.
divrei kivushin. אחינו, Acheinu,
our brethren, okay, we'll bracket the gender issue here. לא נאמר באנשי
נינוה, Lo ne'emar beanshei ninvei,
it does not say by the people of Ninveh, וירא אלהים את
שקם ואת תעניתם, vayar elohim et sakam ve'et ta'anitam, that God saw
their sackcloth and their fast, אלא וירא אלהים את מעשיהם כי שבו
מדרכם הרעה. Ella vayar elohim et ma'aseihem ki shavu midarkam hara'ah. It
says God saw their deeds because they had returned from their evil
way. So we need to take stock of
what we're doing wrong and what we need to correct. ובקבלה הוא
אומר, Uvakabala hu omer, and in the prophets it says, וקרעו לבבכם
ואל בגדיכם, vekiru levavchem ve'al bigdeichem, rend your hearts, not your garments.
So this, all the whatever practices that we're doing should lead to
actual opening of the heart, rending of the heart, of a תשובה.
teshuvah. Now, first of all, it's interesting, yes I was going to
say something, why does it say בקבלה? bakabala? They're both from
נביא, navi, so
actually, right, יונה Yona and יואל Yoel are both from the תרי
עשר. Trei Asar. So they're actually both from the same source, so
why does it say, why does one say he just quoted and
the other says ובקבלה הוא אומר? uvakabala hu omer? So it could
just be that you could have said בקבלה bakabala by the first
one as well, it just didn't fit in as well to the
script. It doesn't say לא נאמר באנשי נינוה lo ne'emar beanshei ninvei
this, אלא, ella, so you need, you're setting up the contrast. You
don't want to say אלא בקבלה הוא אומר, ella bakabala hu omer,
right? So you need that to be, you want to immediately flow
into that. And then when you want to say, 'And it says,'
so the בקבלה bakabala serves as a word of transition. That could
just be an easy reason why it says that. There is some
discussion that maybe the words קבלה kabala are used specifically when the
פסוקים pesukim in נ״ך Nach are sort of directed at, are like
directly giving מוסר mussar as opposed to narrative. So the פסוקים psukim
from נינוה, Ninveh, from יונה, Yona, is narrative which we're learning a
lesson, whereas the פסוק וקרעו לבבכם ואל בגדיכם pasuk vekiru levavchem ve'al
bigdeichem is explicitly sort of giving מוסר. mussar. Maybe that has the,
that is for the term of קבלה, kabala, but it is interesting.
Okay, so he basically says we've got to introspect, we've got to
do תשובה. teshuvah. We don't, yes, we're fasting, but let's not think
that it's just about the external practices, it's really about taking heart
and internalizing it. So there, by the way, is the one place
I think in the whole מסכת masechet that you have
תשובה, teshuvah, sort of as raised up as an issue is this
דרשה drasha of הזקן. hazaken. Now you could say, 'Yes, but that
shows that's all what it's about,' but again, I would question that.
That is certainly one element of it, but here is the one
place where that is mentioned.
So that's what the זקן zaken says. Now,
by the way, the other thing to mention is he speaks about
sackcloth, fasting, and rending garments. Right now, which of those have they
done? Sackcloth, fasting, and rending garments. What do we know? All they've
done is fasting. There's been no mention of sackcloth; sackcloth is never
a ritual in הלכה. halacha. I mean, it's a ritual in all
of תנ״ך, Tanakh, but it's never a ritual in הלכה. halacha. And
rending the garments they haven't done, right? So it's interesting in a
way he's like saying, 'Oh, it's don't rend your garments, rend your
heart.' They're not even rending their garments. But okay, maybe there's a
little bit of an indication that that's what it should be at
that level, but it is interesting noticing sort of the contrast being
set up and they're not doing it anyway. All right. עומדים בתפילה,
Omdim batfila, so that was the דרשה. drasha. Then עמדו בתפילה, amdu
batfila, then they stand up to דאוון. daven. So this is the
proof that you give your sermon right before שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei.
Okay. So you know you got to get people stirred up, get
them in the right mode to be to enter into דאווענינג. davening.
So they gave this דרשה drasha and now they get up to
דאווען. daven. עמדו בתפילה. amdu bitfilah.
מורידים לפני
התיבה זקן ורגיל.
moridim lifnei hateivah zakein
veragil.
What about סמיכת גאולה לתפילה? semichat geulah litfilah?
Well the question is, well which, that's a good question right? Which
what are we talking about? Are we talking about מנחה? mincha? Are
we talking about שחרית? shacharit? Right, it sounds like the assumption is
is that we're talking about שחרית shacharit because it's saying it right
at the beginning and we'll see the twenty-four ברכות, brachot, all of
those are certainly assumed to be in the שחרית shacharit שמונה עשרה.
shemoneh esrei. Although we you know we did say earlier, I'll remind
you that the גמרא gemara said the first half of the day
is a focusing on מילי דמתא millei demata and then the second
half of the day is you know is תפילה. tefilah. So did
they mean to imply that all this was מנחה? mincha? You know,
or do they just mean like even a bigger emphasis of it
was in the מנחה mincha time? It's not exactly clear from that
גמרא gemara how that corresponds you know to this. But yes, it
is interesting. So maybe it means that they you know they went
right into ברכות קריאת שמע. birchos krias shema. I'll remind you that
in the גמרא, gemara, the גמרא gemara? does not have פסוקי דזמרה,
pesukei dezimrah, okay? And the גמרא gemara. does not have the ברכות
השחר, birchos hashachar, you know like the שלא עשניs shelo asani and
the הנותן ליעף כח. hanosein layaeif koach. The גמרא gemara. doesn't have
that as part of the what you say in the שול. shul.
That's like you say when you wake up and when you encounter
those things during the day. So basically דאווענינג davening in the גמרא,
gemara you know what שחרית shacharit looked like in the גמרא? Gemara...
Like what מעריב maariv looks like. Basically it was ברכות קריאת שמע,
birchos krias shema, שמע, shema, you know the ברכות brachos at the
end, שמונה עשרה. shemoneh esrei. That was שחרית shacharit in the גמרא.
Gemara So it's possible you give the דרשה drasha and then you
do שמע shema and שמונה עשרה. shemoneh esrei. You know, so it's,
so it is possible to read this as שמונה עשרה shemoneh esrei
quickly, soon followed. But it is a very good question, like are
we talking about שחרית shacharit or מנחה, mincha, especially based on the
earlier גמרא. Gemara, I think the assumption here is שחרית, shacharit, but
who knows, maybe it's מנחה. mincha. Okay. So, עמדו בתפילה. amdu bitfilah.
Then they rose to דאווען. daven. מורידים לפני התיבה זקן ורגיל. moridim
lifnei hateivah zakein veragil. You bring, you lower down, you bring in
front of the of the ark, somebody, an elderly person who is
accustomed meaning who knows how to דאווען. daven. You know who's able
to דאווען daven well, won't make mistakes, maybe can דאווען daven in
a way that will you know get
people stirred up. ויש לו בנים vayeish lo banim and he has
children. Important, like these are things that sometimes are said in general
by you know a שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur and more particularly by
a שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur like say by the ימים נוראים yamim
noraim where you want the person to really come with the right
type of frame of mind and emotion to be able to help
the ציבור tzibbur and represent the ציבור in their תפילות. So the
idea of course is that if you have children, you know what
it means to really care for others and care for the well-beings
of others, and that sense of like of compassion and responsibility. וביתו
ריקם uveiso reikam and his house is empty. So that's interesting. What
does that mean? Maybe it means he has children and they're all
grown up. He has empty nest syndrome! No, that wouldn't make so
much sense why that would be important. רש״י? Rashi? He doesn't have
to take
care of his kids? What? He's not distracted about that? Maybe, maybe.
רש״י Rashi says that the פשט pshat probably means that he doesn't
have the possessions. He doesn't, so you know he feels he has
that lowly state of mind that you know as opposed to the
way sometimes if we have a lot of possessions it can sort
of puff us up. But the גמרא Gemara will give another explanation.
But somebody who knows what he's doing, who's presumably like elderly because
that will make the community respect him, maybe also because it'll make
him give him like a perspective on sort of life and its
travails, who has the right type of compassion, somebody who really can
bring the right emotional state to the you know to the תפילה.
tefilah. כדי שיהא לבו שלם
בתפילה, kedei sheyehei libo shaleim bitfilah, so his heart should, so he
should be wholehearted in his דאווענינג. davening. Now all of that makes
a lot of sense. Interesting though to note a contrast going on
here. The other זקן, zakein, not necessarily this person, it was הזקן
שבהם, hazakein shebahem, maybe the eldest you know, but anyway the other
זקן zakein said וקרעו לבבכם, vikru levavchem, rend your hearts. This person
is going to be שלם, shaleim, to be לבו שלם libo shaleim
with a full heart. So is your heart complete or is your
heart rent? Which one is it? So it's a little interesting. It
could be the answer is both. It could be rend your hearts
in order to like cut through you know all the armor that
we normally have around it, you know sort of so to get
to the true heart on the inside. It could also be you
know rend your hearts in the in the mode of תשובה teshuvah
and self-reflection,
but you know but that, so there the imagery of a rent
heart whereas a full heart in terms of how we approach God.
Like there's one mode that we're in when we're thinking about our
תשובה teshuvah and what we have to do, and there's another mode
that we're in when we're in the process of of actually reaching
out to God. But it does, it is very suggestive. contrast of
a rent heart and a לבו שלם. libo shalem. Okay. So now
he's leading the שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. ואומר לפניהם עשרים וארבע ברכות
Va'omer lifneihem esrim v'arbah brachot and he says instead of doing the
repetition of the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei 18, or as we said
before maybe 19 in the earlier fasts where he says the ברכה
bracha of עננו, Anenu, here he says 24. י"ח שבכל יום, Yud-Chet
shebechol yom, the standard 18, really 19 but okay, the standard 18,
and I don't even mean 19 for עננו, Anenu, there are 19
ברכות brachot in שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, but okay, let's pretend there
are 18. ומוסיף עליהם עוד שש U'mosif aleihem od sheish and add
six. No. Only in the חזרת הש"ץ. Chazarat Hashatz. Okay. ואלו הן
V'eilu hein and these are the six that are added. And by
the way, I should just say that the we're going to hear
in a minute, but these are added in the same place that
the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur adds עננו. Anenu. It's added between גואל
Goel and רופא. Rofei. So we discussed a little bit the other
day the placement of why it's between גואל Goel and רופא, Rofei,
but that's where these are added exactly. So you can think about
it as עננו Anenu is one is the short version, when it
gets to be serious, you do six ברכות brachot in that place.
Six ברכות. brachot. As I said, do they end in שם ומלכות?
shem u'malchut?
Yes. Yes. So let's take a look. Six ברכות brachot are added.
ואלו הן V'eilu hein and these are
they: זכרונות ושופרות. Zichronot v'Shofrot. So this is interesting. Obviously you should
be thinking about ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, right? The זכרונות Zichronot and
the שופרות, Shofrot, which if you remember from ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
remember that משנה mishnah. which says השופר מאריך והחצוצרות מקצרות, Hashofar maarich
v'hachatzotzrot m'katzrot, you know, and then it said on the
תעניות, חצוצרות מאריך ושופרות מקצרות, chatzotzrot maarich v'shofrot m'katzrot, so there was
this whole idea of that the similar issues of שופר shofar and
we're going to see about the blowing of the שופר shofar or
blowing up of החצוצרות hachatzotzrot and it also spoke about the ברכות
שווה, brachot shaveh, you know, we had שווה יובל ראש השנה shaveh
Yovel Rosh Hashanah for the ברכה, bracha, but also the same idea
of ברכות brachot in the תעניות, that the תעניות were שווה לראש
השנה shaveh l'Rosh Hashanah in the ברכות. brachot. So you do not
make the ברכה bracha of מלכויות, Malchuyot, which is of course irrelevant
here, if anything the whole problem is that we're not, you know,
feeling that connection of מלכות, malchut, but זכרונות Zichronot and שופרות Shofrot
are very relevant. זכרונות, Zichronot, at least the way we have the
נוסח הברכה, nusach habracha, זוכר הברית. Zocher Habrit. God, your distance from
us, remember the covenant, you know, which is makes is our bond,
it's close to us. And so do we, our gearsa, so we'll
see what the משנה's mishnah. גירסא girsa is, not, but our גירסא
girsa on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is, our נוסח nusach on ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah is שומע קול תרועת עמו ישראל ברחמים, Shomeiah kol
truat amo Yisrael b'rachamim, you hear a שופר shofar blast. So the
שופר shofar is the means in which we're trying to reach out
to you, we're trying to reach out בתפילה, bitfila, we're trying to
reach out by blowing the שופר, shofar, we will find out that
they blew the שופר shofar here. So God, it's totally appropriate. Be
close to us, remember us, hear our attempts to reach you, hear
שופר shofar blasts. So that was, those are the first two. Interesting
that they also introduce it, maybe because they're the more standard liturgy,
so therefore you want to start with them. רש"י says not only
would you have the חתימה chatima of the זכרונות Zichronot and שופרות,
Shofrot, guess what you would also say during those? All of the
פסוקים. psukim. So that would be like a powerful way to introduce
it, right, quoting all these פסוקים psukim about what, about God
remember us and God listen to our, listen to our, you know,
שופר, shofar, listen to our attempt to reach you. Okay. So those
are one and two. אל ה' בצרתה לי וקראתי ויענני. El Hashem
batzarata li v'karati v'ya'aneini. And then the other four would be made
up of פרקים בתהילים. prakim b'Tehillim. Okay.
So yes,
we're going to see, there will be a ברכה. bracha. These are
just things that are, it doesn't even just mean you just start
saying the פסוקים. psukim. Like by זכרונות Zichronot you say a lot
of פסוקים psukim too, but you have an opening paragraph. So it's
not exactly clear the entire נוסח הברכה, nusach habracha, but the central
aspect would be the פרק בתהילים perek b'Tehillim that God I have
called you, called to you at a time when I am, you
know, in צרה, tzara, in trouble, and you have answered me. So
again, the idea we're calling to you, answer us. That's ברכה bracha
number three. אשא עיני אל ההרים מאין יבוא עזרי. Essa einai el
heharim m'ayin yavo ezri. I look up to God, I feel like
where is my help going to come from? Again God, we're turning
to you, we're in a state of feeling, you know, distant and
despair, and our total focus is on you. ממעמקים קראתיך ה'. Mima'amakim
k'raticha Hashem. Also again, from the depths I've called out to God.
You do the whole
thing, right, the whole פרק? Presumably they say the whole פרק. תפילה
לעני כי יעטוף Tfila l'ani ki ya'atof and a prayer to a
poor person when he faints, ולפני ה' ישפוך שיחו v'lifnei Hashem yishpoch
sicho and before God pours out his speech. So basically God, we
are praying to you, we're praying to you, please, we look to
you, please answer us. Again, by the way, I do want to
say, and I know I am a little bit belaboring it, none
of these speak to the point of תשובה, teshuva, right? They speak
to the point of we're in trouble, we're calling out to you,
answer us. That is the theme here. Okay. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, לא היה צריך לומר זכרונות ושופרות. lo
haya tzarich lomar Zichronot v'Shofrot. You don't have to say, which presumably
means you shouldn't say, זכרונות ושופרות, Zichronot v'Shofrot, maybe he felt that
that was too evocative of a different mode and something more related
to the, you know, to the feeling of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
and that's not the most appropriate thing to say here. אלא אומר
תחתיהן, Ela omer tachteihen, you say instead the following פסוקים: psukim: רעב
כי יהיה בארץ, Ra'av ki yihyeh ba'aretz, if there's a famine in
the land, that's by מלכים, Melachim, by the תפילה tfila of שלמה.
Shlomo. And דבר כי יהיה *dever ki yihyeh* of this pestilence and
אשר היה דבר ה' אל ירמיהו על דברי הבצרות *asher hayah devar
Hashem el Yirmiyahu al divrei habatzarot*. The word of God was to
ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu* and in the because of the famines. Now, those do
not sound less like calling out to God and more like narratives
or descriptives. So you have to look at the later part of
those פסוקים psukim, *psukim*, so let me actually read them to you
to hear what the power of it is and actually the power
of why he's saying it at the beginning and what's the debate
between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* and the or there's a
תנ"ך *Tanakh* there. I was anyway I was looking it up yesterday
on my no you can give him the תנ"ך *Tanakh*. I had
it here on my so I brought my fancy iPad here. Okay,
so let's take a look at at what these פסוקים psukim, *psukim*
are. So I'll start with the מלכים *Melachim* one. Problem with this
is you can't have two windows open at the same time. Okay,
so and this is because it also addresses the question of why
is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* arguing? Like alright, it's from
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah* but it's very appropriate. What's this
מחלוקת *machlokes* about? So let's listen to these פסוקים psukim, *psukim* and
hear what the מחלוקת *machlokes* might be about. So this is תפילת
שלמה Shlomo. *tfilat Shlomo* when he in the dedication of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash* and we opened actually the מסכת *masechet*
by referring to this פסוק *passuk* where he speaks about how people
will all turn their prayers to you God through this בית *bayis*,
directed towards the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*, but specifically he
spoke about when people are in suffering and there's no rain or
there's pestilence and they're in travail, they will turn their prayers to
you through this house. But let's look exactly what it says. It
says, and this is way at the end, ל"א *lamed-aleph*,
I think. Where is it?
מלכים א' ח' *Melachim Aleph Chet*. Yeah, yeah, I'm in מלכים *Melachim*
first. Okay, so here's what he says. He says so first he
says in ל"א *lamed-aleph*, פסוק ל"א *passuk lamed-aleph*: את אשר יחטא איש
לרעהו ונשא בו אלה ובא אלה לפני מזבחך בבית הזה ואתה תשמע
השמים ועשית ושפטת את עבדיך להרשיע רשע לתת דרכו בראשו ולהצדיק צדיק
*et asher yecheta ish lere'eihu venasha bo alah uva alah lifnei mizbachacha
babayit hazeh ve'atah tishma hashamayim ve'asita veshafatta et avadecha leharshia rasha latet
darko berosho ulehatzdik tzaddik*. Okay, so you right wrong, somebody will turn
to you for justice. ובהנגף עמך ישראל לפני אויב אשר יחטאו לך
ושבו אליך והודו את שמך והתפללו והתחננו אליך בבית הזה ואתה תשמע
השמים *vehenagef amcha Yisrael lifnei oyev asher yechetu lach vashavu eilecha vehodu
et shemecha vehitpalalu vehitchananu eilecha babayit hazeh ve'atah tishma hashamayim*. בהעצר שמים
ולא יהיה מטר כי יחטאו לך והתפללו אל המקום הזה והודו את
שמך ומחטאתם ישובון כי תענם ואתה תשמע השמים וסלחת לחטאת עבדיך ועמך
ישראל כי תורם את הדרך הטובה אשר ילכו בה ונתת מטר על
ארצך אשר נתת לעמך לנחלה *behe'atzer shamayim velo yihyeh matar ki yechetu
lach vehitpalalu el hamakom hazeh vehodu et shemecha
umichatatam
yeshuvun ki ta'aneim ve'atah tishma hashamayim vesalachta lechatat avadecha ve'amcha Yisrael ki
torem
et haderech hatovah asher yelchu vah venatata matar al artzecha asher natata
le'amcha lenachalah*. You show them the right path. רעב ra'av, כי יהיה
בארץ דבר כי יהיה שדפון ירקון ארבה חסיל *ra'av ki yihyeh va'aretz
dever ki yihyeh shidafon yerakon arbeh chasil*. Okay, כל תפילה tefilla כל
תחנה אשר תהיה לכל האדם לכל עמך ישראל אשר ידעון איש נגע
לבבו ופרש כפיו אל הבית הזה ואתה תשמע השמים מכון שבתך וסלחת
ועשית ונתת לאיש ככל דרכיו אשר תדע את לבבו כי אתה ידעת
לבדך את לבב כל בני האדם *kol tfila kol tchina asher tihiyeh
lechol ha'adam lechol amcha Yisrael asher yid'un ish nega levavo ufarash kapav
el habayit hazeh ve'atah tishma hashamayim mechon shivtecha vesalachta ve'asita venatata le'ish
kechol drachav asher teda et levavo ki atah yadata levadecha et levav
kol bnei ha'adam*. Okay, so I think one of the things is,
so Michael asks a very good question, the פסוקים psukim *psukim* right
before דווקא davka *davka* about rain. So I have to imagine, although
again it's funny that he doesn't start there, that that's just one
פסוק *passuk* being quoted and it means quoting like the larger context
of the פסוקים pesukim? *psukim*. Maybe he doesn't want to explicitly quote
the rain because maybe that's too much emphasizes the idea of sin.
These פסוקים pesukim *psukim* here don't explicitly talk about sin and they'll
do תשובה teshuva *tshuva*. So maybe let's not mention to God that
we've been sinning, let's not focus on that, let's just focus on
the end here. But nevertheless what it does say is it's not
just narrative. It says, God, we are going to call out to
you and the end of all these פסוקים pesukim *psukim* are, you're
going to listen to us. So and שלמה Shlomo, *Shlomo* already said,
that's what that's what we do, we turn to you, we pray
to you, God, listen to us. So that's how it makes sense
in terms of a prayer to God. But what dominates in this
whole context is חטא cheit *cheit*, חטא *cheit* and תשובה teshuva *tshuva*.
The reason is because of חטא *cheit*, we do תשובה teshuva *tshuva*,
therefore you respond to us. Similarly if you think about ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu*,
right?
You know, so but in ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu*, which where is it? י"ד
*yud-daled*, right? In ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu* it is אשר היה דבר ה' אל
ירמיהו על דברי הבצרות *asher hayah devar Hashem el Yirmiyahu al divrei
habatzarot*. אבלה יהודה ושעריה אמללו קדרו לארץ וצוחת ירושלים Yerushalayim עלתה *avlah
Yehudah ushe'areha umlalu kadru la'aretz vetzivchat Yerushalayim altah*. Things are terrible. It's
this fast, there's no water in the wells, everybody is in mourning.
בעבור האדמה חתה כי לא היה גשם בארץ בשו אכרים חפו ראשם
*ba'avur ha'adamah chattah ki lo hayah geshem ba'aretz boshu ikarim chafu rosham*.
Okay, so it's all the land is the terrible thing about the
land. Now, פסוק ז' *passuk zayin*: אם עוננו ענו בנו *im avoneinu
anu vanu*, if our sins have answered this is spoken up against
us by the way notice תענית *ta'anis*, עניה *aniyah*, עוננו *avoneinu*, ענו
*anu*, anyway, syncopation here. אם עוננו ענו בנו עשה למען שמך כי
רבו משובותינו לך חטאנו *im avoneinu anu vanu aseh lema'an shemecha ki
rabu meshuvoteinu lecha chatanu*. Because we have turned back, we have sinned
against you. מקוה ישראל ה' מושיעו בעת צרה tzarah. למה תהיה כגר
בארץ וכאורח נטה ללון למה תהיה כאיש נדהם כגבור לא יוכל להושיע
ואתה בקרבנו ה' ושמך עלינו נקרא אל תניחנו *mikveh Yisrael Hashem moshio
be'et tzarah lamah tihiyeh keger va'aretz uche'orach natah lalun lamah tihiyeh ke'ish
nidham kegibor lo yuchal lehoshia ve'atah bekirbeinu Hashem veshimcha aleinu nikra al
tanicheinu*. So what you have here very much is this sense about
God's just. So what you have here very much is this sense
about God's distance. Why are you like this, like a stranger to
us? Why are you like somebody who's not listening to our prayers,
who is callous towards our outcry? So that sense of God, why
are you distant, but again, a theme here is sin. Sin and
תשובה teshuva and acknowledging that that might be what it's about. And
I do not think that that is I did not read through
all of the other פרקים perakim of תהלים Tehillim that are mentioned,
but those פרקים perakim are all about תפילה tefilla and answering תפילה
tefilla and not about sin. So there's a real big difference going
on here, I think, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. is basically saying
number one, the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah theme might not be as
most appropriate, maybe it evokes ראש השנה or whatever, not like it's
completely inappropriate, but maybe the thing that you really need to be
opening with and focusing on is this issue of the תשובה teshuva
theme and have that and to be reflective on that and to
bring that into the conversation. So it's very much possible that part
of this debate here is exactly that, about how much to emphasize
the aspects of sin and תשובה teshuvah. in this process. Okay, so
that's one thing I would put out there as the possible difference.
The other thing I would say is to remind you of the
issue we had just yesterday when it says מתריעין, matri'in, if מתריעין
matri'in means בשופר bashofar or does it mean בעננו? baanenu? And maybe
the other issue that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda? has is it should
all be about תפילה tefillah? and not be about שופר. shofar. You
know, when you use ritual like a thing like a שופר, shofar,
blowing of a שופר, shofar, there's something that is powerful about it,
to focus us, to wake us up, to motivate us. But there's
also something that could allow us a certain amount of oh, we've
done the right acts and therefore things are going to be okay.
You know, if you don't have the ritual, you have to focus
a lot more on did we do enough,
have we gone through the process, have we actually done the תשובה
that we need to do, the prayers that we need to do?
So maybe that fits with רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda, idea also about
focusing on this idea of תשובה and sin. We're not going to
just do this ritual of a שופר shofar or we're not going
to focus on that and think that that's going to solve our
problems. So I think that there could be two things going on
with רבי יהודה. A, he presumably doesn't deny that there was שופר
shofar blasts, but let's not overly focus on that, and B, let's
really put our focus on this issue about sin and תשובה that
really has something that needs to be more priority. Okay, so that's
what I would like to see is going on here in this
debate. Now the גמרא... Gemara. now the משנה mishnah... continues. Okay, so
those were the six... the six ברכות. brachot. Okay.
Okay, where were we? ואומר חותמיהן. v'omer chotmeihen. And now Michael's leaving,
but but here Michael's your answer, they I know you got to
go, goodbye. Anyway, they say the חתימה, chatima, they're not just saying
פסוקים, pesukim? they're not just saying whatever sort of liturgy introduces and
frames these פסוקים, psukim they then say a חתימה chatima of the
ברכה. bracha. על הראשונה הוא אומר, al harishona hu omer, now in
the first חתימה chatima they say, מי שענה את אברהם אבינו בהר
המוריה הוא יענה אתכם וישמע בקול צעקתכם, mi she'ana et Avraham Avinu
behar haMoria hu ya'ane etchem v'yishma bekol tza'akatchem,
the one who answered Abraham should answer you, היום הזה ברוך אתה
ה' גואל ישראל. hayom hazeh baruch ata Hashem goel Yisrael.
Now is this both the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי יהודה?
Yes, now we're back, now this is everybody.
Two different sets of פסוקים,
two different religious themes,
right, but the
same חתימה, chatima,
right, nobody is debating the חתימה. chatima. Okay, but you'll see the
חתימה chatima are very generic, okay. Now, the first חתימה chatima here
גואל ישראל Goel Yisrael is the normal חתימה chatima we make in
שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei of גואל ישראל. Goel Yisrael. So although it
says first, we're really going to count off not six, but seven.
There are six new ones, but in a way we already have
the hook in גואל ישראל Goel Yisrael to create the transition. So
we already bring some of this theme and some of these differences
into גואל ישראל, Goel Yisrael, we say the מי שענה לאברהם אבינו
mi she'ana l'Avraham Avinu and גואל ישראל Goel Yisrael and then that
idea of גואל, goel, redeem us, is then carries us into the
new six ברכות brachot and this is the hook that gets us
there. Okay?
So by the גואל ישראל Goel Yisrael you have the standard נוסח
nusach of גואל ישראל, Goel Yisrael, right?
That's, here's גואל Goel and here's רפאנו, Refaeinu, okay? These are the
standard ones and then we're going to add six, okay? But the
hook that you put into here is
מי שענה לאברהם, mi she'ana l'Avraham, הוא יענה, hu ya'ane, הוא יענה.
hu ya'ane. So that's the hook, but basically it's גואל ישראל, Goel
Yisrael, רפאנו, Refaeinu, and six new ones. Yes.
So the implication is that the whole, you know, מי שענה אברהם
mi she'ana Avraham etc., that that's basically in the same way as
we put in a פיוט piyut like זכרנו לחיים Zochreinu L'Chayim that
that would go in there and then you would do גואל ישראל.
Goel Yisrael.
Exactly, exactly. But what's important to note is because it immediately precedes
the ברכה, bracha, you know, חז"ל had a big thing that the...
that the חתימה chatima has to be, you know, like the last
line has to be מעין החתימה. me'ein hachatima. So the theme of
the ברכה bracha really connects most powerfully to how you to what
you said right before the חתימה. chatima. So by saying this, it's
not just somewhere like in the middle, like I'm responding because you
said is it like you're saying זכרנו לחיים. Zochreinu L'Chayim. You're saying
it right before the חתימה, chatima, it also frames
the חתימה. chatima. Okay? So that the גואל ישראל Goel Yisrael now...
Exactly, exactly, exactly. So they also fixed it for Rosh Hashanah too,
so they
also fixed it.
Right, well this became- but the סליחות selichot came later. Like this
became the basis for, you know, the סליחות. selichot. So the part
of the סליחות selichot that you sort of do at the end
with- I don't know, some people say they like that part. In
Hebrew they understand it, they focus on it a lot. For me,
it's like- it's like I just zip through that. By then anyway
we're in a rush, we've just spent all this time on the
earlier part. To me, it's like מי שענה, mi she'ana, מי שענה,
mi she'ana, like okay, there's not a change here, I've just totally
scandalized over this. Anyway, but the point is, it is the earliest-
it is the earliest of these תפילות. Okay. So that's גואל
ישראל.
Goel
Yisrael. Okay, על השניה הוא אומר, al hashniyah hu omer, the second
of the changes, but really it's the first of the new ones,
הוא אומר: hu omer: מי שענה לאבותינו על ים סוף הוא יענה
אתכם וישמע קול צעקתכם היום הזה ברוך אתה ה׳ זוכר הנשכחות. mi
she'ana l'avoteinu al yam suf, hu ya'aneh etchem veyishma kol tza'akatchem hayom
hazeh. Baruch atah Hashem, zocher hanishkachot. So you'll remember now we're assuming
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, not Rabbi Yehuda, זכרונות Zichronot and שופרות. Shofarot.
Okay, those are the sort of core at the center. It's
מי שענה לאבותינו, mi she'ana l'avoteinu, right? במצרים, bemitzrayim, is that it?
לאבותינו
במצרים. l'avoteinu bemitzrayim. And the חתימה chatimah is what? What's the חתימה?
chatimah?
זוכר הנשכחות. zocher hanishkachot. Interesting it's not זוכר הברית. zocher habrit. Does
that mean that the חתימה chatimah they had on Rosh Hashanah also
was זוכר הנשכחות? zocher hanishkachot? Not so clear, because in other places
we equate the ברכות brachot and we're calling these זכרונות. Zichronot.
So maybe they had- oh, I'm sorry.
על ים סוף. al yam suf. על ים סוף. al yam suf.
Okay,
so I'll talk in a minute about the way the חתימה chatimah
connects to the מי שענה mi she'ana to the whatever, you know,
but I'll talk about that in a minute. But let's first just
get the facts down. Okay. But I do want also to point
out, does this suggest that that was also
the חתימה chatimah they had on Rosh Hashanah?
Not clear. Let's keep on going. Okay, על ים סוף. al yam
suf. הוא יענה אתכם. hu ya'aneh etchem. Okay, ברוך אתה ה׳ זוכר
הנשכחות. Baruch atah Hashem, zocher hanishkachot. על השלישית הוא אומר: al hashlishit
hu omer: מי שענה ליהושע בגלגל הוא יענה אתכם וישמע בקול צעקתכם
היום הזה ברוך אתה ה׳ שומע תרועה.
mi she'ana l'Yehoshua b'Gilgal, hu ya'aneh etchem veyishma bekol tza'akatchem hayom hazeh.
Baruch atah Hashem,
shome'a teruah.
Our גרסא girsa for Rosh Hashanah is שומע תרועת עמו ישראל ברחמים.
shome'a teruat amo Yisrael berachamim. So again, was that their ברכה? bracha?
Not clear. But this is מי שענה ליהושע בגלגל. mi she'ana l'Yehoshua
b'Gilgal. Right now, בגלגל, b'Gilgal, and then what's the חתימה? chatimah? This
one? שומע תרועה. shome'a teruah. שומע תרועה. shome'a teruah. Okay, so by-
so this one we understand, right? When was Yehoshua answered בגלגל, b'Gilgal,
right? So that- was Gilgal Yericho? It was Yericho, right? No? Yeah,
I'm pretty sure. What's the Rashi says? I was assuming it was.
Yeah, yeah, it's Yericho. Right. So this is Yericho.
Yehoshua was
answered, right, with the שופרות.
shofarot. So this- everything works. This is
about שופר, shofar, this is about שופר, shofar, it all ties in.
This theme all works together.
Here the חתימה chatimah
works, but it's not- does it connect to the לאבותינו על ים
סוף? l'avoteinu al yam suf? Not so clear. Okay, but we'll get
back to that. Okay, so that- that one clearly it all ties
together. Okay, על הרביעית הוא אומר, al harevi'it hu omer, on the
fourth- the third of the new ones, he says: מי שענה לשמואל
במצפה הוא יענה אתכם וישמע בקול צעקתכם היום הזה ברוך אתה ה׳
שומע צעקה. mi she'ana li'Shmuel baMitzpah, hu ya'aneh etchem veyishma bekol tza'akatchem
hayom hazeh. Baruch atah Hashem, shome'a tze'akah. So the fourth one- the
third of the new ones was אל ה׳ בצרתה לי קראתי ויענני.
el Hashem batzarata li karati vaya'aneni. Okay, so that's a פרק תהילים:
perek Tehillim: אל ה׳ בצרתה לי קראתי ויענני. el Hashem batzarata li
karati vaya'aneni. And the מי שענה mi she'ana is who? מי שענה
mi she'ana was who? With- לשמואל. li'Shmuel. לשמואל במצפה. li'Shmuel baMitzpah. Okay,
לשמואל במצפה. li'Shmuel baMitzpah. And the חתימה chatimah is what? שומע צעקה.
shome'a tze'akah. Okay, not clear here how it all ties together. Why
is צעקה tze'akah unique to Shmuel? Is צעקה tze'akah tied into- into
אל ה׳ בצרתה לי? el Hashem batzarata li? Right, it doesn't say
שומע קריאה, shome'a keriah, it says קראתי. karati. So we will get
back to that. Okay, so there's a question of how these things-
do they really tie together or not? So I'll- we'll get back
and unpack that. Let's again just continue- continue with this. על החמישית
הוא אומר: al hachamishit hu omer:
מי שענה לאליהו בהר הכרמל הוא יענה אתכם וישמע בקול צעקתכם היום
הזה ברוך אתה ה׳ שומע תפילה. mi she'ana l'Eliyahu b'Har Karmel, hu
ya'aneh etchem veyishma bekol tza'akatchem hayom hazeh. Baruch atah Hashem, shome'a tefillah.
Okay, so the פסוקים that you would say on this one would
be אשא עיני אל ההרים. essa einai el heharim. אשא עיני
אל ההרים. essa einai el heharim. Okay,
it's- and it's מי שענה לאליהו. mi she'ana l'Eliyahu.
Right, לאליהו. l'Eliyahu. And what's the חתימה? chatimah? שומע תפילה. shome'a tefillah.
Now here- it's also not clear why is- why is the language
of תפילה? tefillah Is that exactly, you know- אשא עיני אל ההרים-
essa einai el heharim is that exactly a language here? Is that
exactly a language by Eliyahu? What is- how does this connect to
Eliyahu? I'll give you one- one hint to this, which
is- So the הר har here at least ties it into the
הרים. harim. Okay, but how that exactly ties into the חתימה, chatimah,
again, not totally clear. Let's go on.
Total confrontation.
Yeah,
okay.
But why not say זעקה ze'akah here and תפילה tefillah there? That's
my point. Is it just that you need a different חתימה chatimah
and there's nothing special about it, or is even the exact word
tie in? That's the question. רש״י Rashi addresses it. We're going to
answer the question, I just want to point it out. Okay. על
החמישית הוא אומר, Al hachamishit hu omer, are we on the חמישית?
chamishit? No.
על השישית, Al hashishit, right, הוא אומר, hu omer, מי שענה את
יונה ממעי הדגה הוא יענה אתכם וישמע בקול צעקתכם היום הזה ברוך
אתה ה׳ העונה בעת צרה. Mi she'ana et Yonah mib'ei hadagah hu
ya'aneh etchem v'yishma b'kol tza'akatchem hayom hazeh Baruch atah Hashem ha'oneh b'eit
tzarah. So what were the פסוקים? The פסוקים were ממעמקים קראתיך ה׳.
Mi-ma'amakim keratikah Hashem. Okay,
so that seems pretty clear, קראתיך, keratikah, okay,
and this is מי שענה Mi she'ana with יונה Yonah and ממעי
הדגה. mib'ei hadagah. And what is the
חתימה? chatimah? העונה בעת צרה. Ha'oneh b'eit tzarah. So again, what's clear
here is, what's clear is the tie-in seems to be ממעי הדגה
mib'ei hadagah ties into ממעמקים, mi-ma'amakim, right? So that seems to sort
of be clear. Okay, but again, the question of העונה בעת צרה,
ha'oneh b'eit tzarah, is that just you needed a different חתימה chatimah
and that doesn't have a unique, a specific thematic tie-in, or does
even the חתימה chatimah have a thematic tie-in? Again, I'll go back
and tell you what רש״י Rashi says on that in a minute.
These are all part of the צרה.
That's true. These are all part of the, right, of the שיר
המעלות. Shir Hama'alot. על השביעית הוא אומר, Al hashvi'it hu omer, so
maybe you mean in the sense of like going up and, you
know, because the שיר המעלות Shir Hama'alot for חז״ל Chazal raises the
idea of like going up to, you know, the מקדש Mikdash and
the steps leading up to the מקדש. Mikdash. So recreating the connection
to the Temple and to God and getting close to God. That's
a very lovely point. That's a very lovely point. And it also
goes back to the point I was saying that all of these
are about God answering us and being close, not about חטא and
תשובה. Okay. Yes.
But העונה בעת צרה,
ha'oneh
b'eit
tzarah, that ties, יונה Yonah is in the דג dag and he's
in an עת צרה. eit tzarah. Right.
Right, but right, he's in an עת צרה. eit tzarah. But you
know, other people were also in an עת צרה. eit tzarah. You
know, why is he more... anyway. על השביעית הוא אומר, Al hashvi'it
hu omer, מי שענה את דוד ושלמה בנו בירושלים הוא יענה אתכם
וישמע בקול צעקתכם היום הזה ברוך אתה ה׳ המרחם על הארץ. Mi
she'ana et David u'Shlomo b'no b'Yerushalayim hu ya'aneh etchem v'yishma b'kol tza'akatchem
hayom hazeh Baruch atah Hashem hamerachem al ha'aretz. So here's interesting, the
פסוקים that you quoted are תפילה לעני כי יעטוף, Tefillah l'ani ki
ya'atof, right?
תפילה לעני. Tefillah l'ani.
It connects to דוד ושלמה בנו בירושלים. David u'Shlomo b'no b'Yerushalayim.
And where exactly were they in trouble when they cried out? That
needs questioning. And the חתימה chatimah is מרחם על הארץ. merachem al
ha'aretz. So this is also very curious
because that's not clear how מרחם על הארץ merachem al ha'aretz connects
to תפילה לעני tefillah l'ani and דוד ושלמה בנו בירושלים David u'Shlomo
b'no b'Yerushalayim connects to תפילה לעני כי יעטוף. tefillah l'ani ki ya'atof.
This one is less clear. So let's, so again, for most of
these it's pretty clear I think how the מי שענהs mi she'ana
have a tie-in, whether the חתימות chatimahs is just a need to
create some difference or does the חתימה chatimah have a thematic tie-in
is not clear. I'll tell you what רש״י Rashi says. Okay, so
here,
let's start with the זכרונות. zichronot. Why, how does מי שענה לאבותינו
על ים סוף Mi she'ana l'avoteinu al Yam Suf tie in? So
רש״י Rashi says,
let me see what רש״י Rashi says.
Okay, רש״י Rashi says, five lines down in the wide lines, לפיכך
אומרו בזכרונות לפי שהיו ישראל נשכחים במצרים כמה שנים ונתייאשו מן הגאולה.
L'fikach omro bizichronot l'fi shehayu Yisrael nishkachim b'Mitzrayim kamah shanim v'nitya'ashu min
hage'ulah. So God remembers them after hundreds of
years that there was a long period where it seems they had
been totally forgotten and then they were remembered. Okay, so he ties
that all into נשכחות אבותינו זכרונות. nishkachot avoteinu zichronot. That's a very
nice thing. שופרות, Shofrot, everything ties in. How about ברכה berakhah number
three about ושמואל במצפה, u'Shmuel baMitzpah, where is the tie-in here between
the theme and the person and the פסוקים? So רש״י Rashi for
that says, it is... no,
that's אליהו. Eliyahu. ו... okay.
So he says this on אליהו Eliyahu בהר הכרמל, כנגד עשירי הרים,
keneged asiri harrim, וכן כולם לפי עניין המזמורים, v'chen kulam l'fi inyan
hamizmorim, אליהו נענה בהר הכרמל מעין עשירי הרים, Eliyahu ne'eneh b'Har HaCarmel
me'ein asiri harrim, ושמואל במצפה דכתיב קרא ובעין אל ה׳ בצרתה לי.
u'Shmuel baMitzpah dikhtiv kra u'va'ein el Hashem b'tzarasah li. So רש״י Rashi
doesn't help you so much there. Okay, everybody, you know,
it's all tied into צר tzar and answering. So רש״י Rashi there
does not help so much on why דווקא davka, to use the
phrase here of where is it, of שומע תפילה Shomea Tefillah as
opposed to, you know, שומע זעקה. Shomea ze'akah. You know, and why
this ties in דווקא, davka you know, this שמואל Shmuel ties in
דווקא to בצרתה לי, b'tzarasah li, could tie into, you know, a
lot of these are interchangeable. So not all of them basically are
uniquely tied in, some of them you just need some variation and
some difference, but there are most of the time. or there are
a lot of areas which they are tied in, so let's just
go on, so we have this which, the שמואל Shmuel one which
seems the most generic, we have the אליהו one which certainly ties
in to the הר הכרמל. Har Hakarmel. The שומע תפילה Shomeiah Tefillah
might just have been a somewhat of a... does רש״י Rashi say
it has the language of... oh no, I'm sorry, if you look
at the next רש״י: Rashi: ממאה דקה, mi-mei'ah dakkah, ממעמקים קראתיך ה׳,
Mima'amakim keraticha Hashem, עונה בעת צרה, oneh be'eis tzara, שכן כתיב ביונה
קראתי מצרה לי, shekein kesiv biYona karasi mitzara li, ובשמואל כתיב ויצעק
אל ה׳, u-vishmuel kesiv vayitz'ak el Hashem, ובאליהו כתיב ענני, u-ve-eliyahu kesiv
aneni, זו
תפילה. zo tefillah. So that... that was again the weakest. But what
רש״י Rashi shows is צעקה tza'akah because by שמואל Shmuel there's a
language of זעקה. ze'akah. It says by שמואל Shmuel and that's שומע
צעקה. shomeiah tza'akah. And by... where were we... by יונה Yona it
says... where was it... בצרה שלו, be-tzara shelo, right?
מצרה לי. mi-tzara li. So... מצרה
לי mi-tzara li and that ties into עונה בעת צרה. oneh be'eis
tzara. So there's a little swath of some places which not a
hundred percent tied in to every single aspect, but you see a
much tighter connection of the פסוקים of the מי שענהs mi she-anah
and of the choice of the חתימה. chatimah. One last comment
about דוד Dovid and שלמה. When did they cry out and when
were they answered? So if you take a look at רש״י, Rashi,
ועל השביעי, ve-al ha-shevi'i, four lines from the bottom, מפורש בגמרא מאי
שביעי מי שענה דוד ויהי רעב בימי דוד שלוש שנים שנה אחר
שנה. meforesh ba-gemara mai shevi'i mi she-anah Dovid vayehi ra'av bimei Dovid
shalosh shanim shana achar shana.
So there was a רעב, ra'av. so that's directly relevant to what's
going on now, I'm in a fear of a רעב. ra'av Okay.
ושלמה כשכניס ארון לבית קדשי הקדשים, u-Shlomo kesh'hichnis aron le-veis kodshei ha-kodashim,
okay,
which is fascinating. How is that connected? It's connected because that has
to do with the idea of God's connecting to God and the
closest to God and not just about the... the famine and the
rain. אי נמי רעב כי יהיה בארץ, ee nami ra'av ki yihyeh
ba-aretz, or in the תפילה tfila of שלמה, he mentions the idea
of there being a famine, right? That was quoted earlier by רבי
יהודה, and that would also maybe be alluded to or mentioned here.
ולפיכך חותם מרחם על הארץ, u-le-fi-chach choseim merachem al ha-aretz, שהן התפללו
על ארץ ישראל ותפילה לעני כי יעטוף להניח דוחק גשמים, she-hein hitpalelu
al Eretz Yisrael u-tefillah le-ani ki ya'atof lahania dochak geshamim, because it
says בהעצר גשמים. be-he-atzar geshamim.
So what רש״י Rashi says here is this last one is the
most specific, because here תפילה לעני כי יעטוף tefillah le-ani ki ya'atof
it says בהעצר גשמים. be-he-atzar geshamim. It's related to that. דוד Dovid
and שמואל Shmuel were about רעב ra'av and therefore it's מרחם על
הארץ. merachem al ha-aretz. We go from a very generic, where God,
we're calling out to you, answer us, to really hitting home and
here is really what we're afraid of and here's really what's going
on and being much much more specific, but only at the last
one. Which again emphasizes, I would say, how much a broader theme
is God answering us and the focus on the immediate issue of
the רעב and the rain is, you know, you know, is proportionally
much smaller. Okay, back to the משנה. Mishna, Back to the משנה.
Mishna מעשה בימי רבי חלפתא, maaseh bi-yemei Rebbi Chalafta, turn the עמוד...
who knew it would take us almost the whole hour to read
through half of the משנה... Mishna okay, מעשה בימי רבי חלפתא ורבי
חנניה בן תרדיון שעבר אחד לפני התיבה. maaseh bi-yemei Rebbi Chalafta ve-Rebbi
Chananya ben Teradyon she-avar echad lifnei ha-teivah. So they were doing one
of this and a person came in front of the שליח ציבור
shliach tzibbur started, וגמר את הברכה כולה, ve-gamar es ha-berakhah kula, he
finished the ברכה berakhah of גואל ישראל, Goel Yisrael, let's say the
first one, ולא ענו אחריו אמן. ve-lo anu acharaiv amen. They didn't
say אמן. amen. תקעו כהנים, tik'u kohanim,
and then somebody got up and said, כהנים, kohanim, blow, תקעו, tik'u,
and they blow, ותקעו... ve-taka'u... ותקעו, ve-taka'u, excuse me. מי שענה את
אברהם אבינו בהר המוריה, mi she-anah es Avraham Avinu be-Har ha-Moriah,
which is what you say by גואל ישראל, Goel Yisrael, הוא יענה
אתכם וישמע בקול צעקתכם היום הזה. hu ya'aneh eschem ve-yishma be-kol tza'akaschem
ha-yom ha-zeh.
And then he says the מי שענה. mi she-anah. הריעו בני אהרן
הריעו. hari'u bnei Aharon hari'u. And then somebody, presumably not the בעל
תפילה, baal tefillah, רש״י Rashi says it was like the... the שמש,
shamash, but... you know, the גבאי, gabbai, but anyway, so somebody then
said, do a תרועה, teruah, and presumably then they did a תרועה.
teruah. Okay. So what's different here? What's different is A, they didn't
say אמן. amen. B, they left the מי שענה mi she-anah for
after the חתימה, chatimah, not integrated into the חתימה, chatimah, and they
gave it this whole thing of the תקיעות שופרות tekios shofros that
gave it its weight. So we actually had like twelve things going
on, you know? You had the new ברכות, berakhos, and then the
מי שענהs mi she-anah outside of the ברכות, berakhos, you know, wrapped
together with the תקיעות tekios and the תרועות. teruos. All right, so
that's what they were doing. ו- וישמע בקול ve-yishma be-kol so... okay.
מי שענה את אבותינו על ים סוף הוא יענה אתכם וישמע בקול
צעקתכם היום הזה. mi she-anah es avoseinu al Yam Suf hu ya'aneh
eschem ve-yishma be-kol tza'akaschem ha-yom ha-zeh. And then presumably they went and
they did the... you know, the same thing for the second and
the third and so on. וכשבא דבר אצל חכמים... u-che-she-ba davar eitzel
chachamim... by the way, it's interesting that it has the כהנים kohanim
doing it, which evokes the idea of the כהנים kohanim blowing the
חצוצרות, chatzotzros, and the חצוצרות chatzotzros were על הצר הצורר אתכם, al
ha-tzar ha-tzoreir eschem,
although here it is שופרות. shofros. But in other places it emphasizes...
no, actually it doesn't say שופר, shofar, it just says תקעו tik'u
and הריעו. hari'u. So... and we do know that חצוצרות chatzotzros are
more emphasized by תענית over שופרות. shofros. So again, another thing to
note is that it is כהנים kohanim that are doing it. Okay.
וכשבא הדבר אצל חכמים אמרו לא היו נוהגים כן אלא בשער מזרח
ובהר הבית. uksheba hadavar etzel chachamim amru lo hayu nohagim ken ela
besha'ar mizrach uvehar habayit. No,
that's only what we do in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. or
in the environs of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Now what's that?
So you might say it's the blowings, it's the תקיעה tki'ah and
the תרועה. tru'ah. We're going to see in the גמרא Gemara that
although not mentioned in this משנה, Mishna תקיעה tki'ah and תרועה tru'ah
was even in all, like even outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash,
It was done, it was done when together with the twenty-four ברכות.
brachot. So according to the גמרא, what's being sort of critiqued here
is not the תקיעות tki'ot and the תרועות, tru'ot, but not answering
אמן amen and maybe doing the מי שענהs mi she'ana outside of
the context of the ברכה. bracha. But גמרא does not feel that
what is being contested here is the blowings, it's תקיעה tki'ah and
the תרועה, tru'ah, it's the not answering אמן amen and maybe doing
it outside of the ברכה. bracha. It's possible to read this משנה
Mishna very differently. I would say the משנה Mishna has not mentioned
that you blow the שופר. shofar. A very, a very legitimate read
of this משנה is that the issue at stake is blowing the
שופר shofar or blowing the חצוצרות chatzoztrot and whether you would do
that outside of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash We'll see more of
that in the גמרא. Okay. ובהר- now שלוש תעניות הראשונות אנשי משמר
mishmar מתענים ולא משלימים. Now notice by the way how this משנה
is structured. We've raised the issue of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash
לא היו נוהגים כן אלא בבית המקדש. lo hayu nohagim ken ela
b'Beit HaMikdash. We ended the תפילות with שלמה בירושלים. Shlomo b'Yerushalayim. So
the מקדש Mikdash connection is there. As you mentioned, you know, there
was also שיר המעלות, Shir HaMa'alot, these פרקים prakim בתהילים. prakim b'Tehillim.
And now we're going to talk about how this would be participated,
those in ירושלים and when they're, you know, in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash. would be connecting to this fast and participating in the
fast to the degree that it made sense. So again this connection
to the מקדש Mikdash is a dominant
theme. אנשי משמר מתענים ולא משלימים ואנשי בית אב לא היו מתענים
כלל. anshei mishmar mit'anim v'lo mashlimim v'anshei beit av lo hayu mit'anim
klal. So in the first three, the כוהנים kohanim that would serve
that week would fast but they would not complete the fast, because
you know they might be needed to help out with the עבודה.
avoda. And the people that were working that day, אנשי בית אב
anshei beit av would not fast at all. I guess they got
to work that day. But there would be still some degree of
connecting to the fasting. שלוש שניות shalosh shniyot and the second group
of the three fasts, which are more weighty and things are more
serious, אנשי משמר מתענים ומשלימים ואנשי בית אב מתענים ולא משלימים. anshei
mishmar mit'anim umashlimim v'anshei beit av mit'anim v'lo mashlimim. It all goes
up one level. So the people who are on call that week
but not working that day would fast for the full fast, and
the people that are working that day would fast but they would
break it sometime in the afternoon when they really needed their strength.
שבע אחרונות, sheva achronot, the last seven, אלו ואלו מתענים ומשלימים. elu
v'elu mit'anim umashlimim. Then everybody would fast. That is the huge communal
sort of tragedy. Even the כוהנים kohanim in the בית המקדש have
to be fasting. By the way, interesting to think that the ארון
gets the ashes and when you're doing this, and the גמרא says
you're doing this only in the last seven. And in the מקדש,
Mikdash, the כוהנים kohanim who are also seen as כלי קודש klei
kodesh and they're inside the מקדש Mikdash are fasting in the last
seven as well. So sort of bringing our connection to the מקדש
Mikdash but also that sense of maybe God is also, you know,
experiencing this distance as well, so even in the מקדש Mikdash the
fasting is taking place.
And not only in the structure, the first three are Monday, Thursday,
Monday, the second—we'll get to that. We'll get to that. That's coming
up. Okay. דברי רבי יהושע, divrei Rabi Yehoshua, that's what רבי יהושע
Rabi Yehoshua says, וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, and חכמים chachamim say the
basic same idea except one degree, one notch down, one notch less
severe. שלוש תעניות הראשונות אלו ואלו לא היו מתענים כלל. shalosh ta'aniyot
harishonot elu v'elu lo hayu mit'anim klal. The first three not done
at all in the בית המקדש. שלוש שניות אנשי משמר מתענים ולא
משלימים ואנשי בית אב לא
היו מתענים כלל. shalosh shniyot anshei mishmar mit'anim v'lo mashlimim v'anshei beit
av lo hayu mit'anim klal. The next three, the people in the
משמר would fast but not a full fast, and the people that
were on duty that day would not fast at all. שבע אחרונות,
sheva achronot, the last seven, אנשי משמר מתענים ומשלימים, anshei mishmar mit'anim
umashlimim,
that those that were on call for the week would fast through
a full fast. ואנשי בית אב מתענים ולא משלימים, v'anshei beit av
mit'anim v'lo mashlimim, and the people of the בית אב beit av
they had to work. So even on the last seven, you know,
they're working in the מקדש, Mikdash, they're trying to help with this
whole idea of, you know, serving God and connecting to God in
God's house, so they would not, even in the last seven they
would not complete the fast. Okay. So that's the issue of fasting.
I think what I'm going to do now is we'll stop now
because the next part of the משנה really goes on to a
very different theme, seems only loosely connected. We'll talk about that tomorrow.
It already didn't take us long to fall back behind. But anyway,
in terms of המשתתף בצרה, hamishtatef b'tzara, let us again say this
תפילה for those that are, for the young boys, for the young
men that are in captivity. מי שבירך אבותינו אברהם יצחק ויעקב אשר
הוציא את יוסף מבור תחתיות וענה לדניאל בגוב האריות אל שומע לצעקת
אבות ואמהות הפותח בכל עת שערי דמעות הוא ישמור וישגיח על הנערים
החטופים יעקב נפתלי בן רחל דבורה גלעד מיכאל בן בת גלים איל
בן איריס תשורה בתוך שאר נדחי עמנו. Mi shebeirach avoteinu Avraham Yitzchak
v'Ya'akov asher hotzi et Yosef mibor tachtiyot v'anah l'Daniel b'gov ha'arayot el
shomei'a l'tza'akat avot v'imahot hapotei'ach b'chol eit sha'arei dma'ot hu yishmor v'yashgiach
al hane'arim hachatufim Ya'akov Naftali ben Rachel Devorah Gilad Michael ben Bat
Galim Eyal ben Iris Teshurah b'toch shear nidchei ameinu. וצבותינו. v'tzivoteinu. אל
רחום וחנון שומר ישראל El rachum v'chanun shomeir Yisrael אשר לא ינום
ולא יישן asher lo yanum v'lo yishan תוציאם מצרה לרווחה totzi'eim mitzara
l'revacha מאפלה לאורה mei'afela l'ora ומשעבוד לגאולה umeshibud l'geulah ותחזירם לחיק אבותיהם
ואימותיהם v'tachzirem l'cheik avoteihem v'imoteihem בבריאות ובשלום. bivriut uv'shalom. בזכות אבותינו תושיע
בנינו bizchut avoteinu toshia baneinu ויקיים בהם מה שכתוב viyikayeim bahem mah
shekatuv הוציאה ממסגר נפשי להודות את שמך hotzia mimasger nafshi l'hodot et
shemecha השתא בעגלא ובזמן קריב hashta ba'agala uvizman kariv ונאמר אמן. v'nomar
amen. Did you hear that?